A Finding Aid to the John Weichsel Papers Concerning the People's Art Guild, 1905-1929, in the Archives of American Art aaa.weicjohn
Archives of American Art
John Weichsel papers concerning the People's Art Guild
1905-1929
aaa.weicjohn
Archives of American Art
0.6 Linear feet
The John Weichsel papers concerning the People's Art Guild measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1905-1929. the papers consist almost entirely of the records of the People's Art Guild, founded by Weichsel, and include administrative records, correspondence, writings and notes, business and financial records, printed material, and artwork.
Weichsel, John, 1870-1946
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1915-1917 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1905-1922 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1915-circa 1919 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Business and Financial Records, 1915-1917 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1915-1929 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 6: Artwork, 1915-1916 (1 folder; Box 2)
Biographical/Historical note
John Weichsel (1870-1946) was an arts administrator and founded the artists' cooperative People's Art Guild of New York City in 1915.
John Weichsel was born in Poland and ultimately settled in New York City. The People's Art Guild was founded by Weichsel as an artist's cooperative focused on improving and expanding knowledge of art and the art world among the general public, believing this would increase art appreciation and patronage.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1960 and 1963 by Dr. H. S. Weichsel and John Weichsel, the son and grandson of Dr. John Weichsel. At an unknown later date, grandson John Weichsel donated his 1965 thesis on the Peoples Art Guild.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection were microfilmed on reels N/60-1-N/60-2, 3, and 1079. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan. Researchers are advised that the microfilm does not reflect the current order of the collection and may be incomplete.
Scope and Contents note
The John Weichsel papers concerning the People's Art Guild measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1905-1929. The papers consist almost entirely of the records of the People's Art Guild, founded by Weichsel, and include administrative records, correspondence, writings and notes, business and financial records, printed material, and artwork.
People's Art Guild records include the constitution, membership lists, and correspondence with Gifford Beal, George Bellows, Oscar Bluemner, Stuart Davis, Robert Delaunay, Leon Kroll, Standon Macdonald-Wright, Jules Pascin, John Sloan, Willard Wright and Marguerite and William Zorach, among others. Writings about the Peoples Art Guild are by Weichsel and his grandson John Weichsel. There are also lists of artists and works of art. Also found are very scattered business and financial records, printed materials, and artwork in the form of sketches for exhibition announcements.
Beal, Gifford, 1879-1956; Bellows, George, 1882-1925; Bluemner, Oscar, 1867-1938; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; Delaunay, Robert, 1885-1941; Kroll, Leon, 1884-1974; Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973; Pascin, Jules, 1885-1930; People's Art Guild.; Sloan, John, 1871-1951; Van Dine, S. S.; Weichsel, John, 1938?-; Zorach, Marguerite, 1887-1968; Zorach, William, 1877-1966; Art--Societies, etc.--New York (State)--New York; Arts administrators, New York (State) -- New York; Sketches
- Administrative Records, 1915-1917; Series 1; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are records relating to the administration of John Weichsel's People's Art Guild including a constitution of the organization and membership lists.
  - Constitution, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1905-1922; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Found is scattered professional correspondence relating to John Weichsel's People's Art Guild. Letters concern works of art lent to the organization and praise for Weichsel. Also found are People's Art Guild form letters and one letter from Eva Weichsel to her husband. Correspondents include John H. Alger, Gifford Beal, George Bellows, Thomas Hart Benton, Oscar Bluemner, Horace Brodzky, Glenn O. Coleman, Stuart Davis, Robert Delaunay, Henry Glintenkamp, Samuel Halpert, Robert Henri, Leon Kroll, Adelaide Lawson (Gaylor), Florence N. Levy, Stanton Macdonald Wright, Gus Mager, Henry A. Mathes, William Meyerowitz, Kenneth H. Miller, Mary H. Mowbray-Clarke, Jerome Myers, Elie Nadelman, John F. Parker, Jules Pascin, Abraham Phillips (Tromka), Maurice Prendergast, Man Ray, John Sloan, Maurice Sterne, Alfred Stieglitz, Abraham Walkowitz, Max Weber, Willard H. Wright (S.S. Van Dine), Marguerite and William Zorach.
  - A, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    John Alger
  - B, 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Elisabeth Bartholow
    Gifford Beal
    Maurice Becker
    George Bellows
    Thomas Hart Benson
    Oscar Bluemner
    J. Van Gogh Bonger
    Horace Brodzsky
  - C, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Caroline Caffin
    Archie Coates
    Glenn Coleman
  - D, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stuart Davis
    Amelia Defies
    Robert Delauney
    Anna Drayton
    Maurice Dubonnet
  - E, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Robert Elzy
  - F, 1916-circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Albert Feinberg
    Walter Frankl
    Freuh
  - G, 1915-1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Henry Glintenkamp
    Carl Grabo
    Mrs. Guggenheimer
  - H, 1915-circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Samuel Halpert
    Robert Henri
  - K, circa 1915-1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    J. Katzenbaum
    Eva Katzman
    Albert Kennedy
    Henry Kent
    Leon Kroll
  - L, 1917-1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Adelaide Lawson
    Sam Lewisohn
    Florence Levy
    I. Lichtenstein
  - M, 1915-1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Stanton Macdonald-Wright
    P. Macdougall
    Gus Mager
    Dr. J. L. Magnes
    Man Ray
    Henry Mathes
    William Meyerowitz
    Kenneth Miller
    The Moderinist
    Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke
    Jerome Meyers
  - N, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Eli Nadelman
    Edward Nagle
    Abraham Neumann
    New York Public Library
  - P, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    John F. Parker
    Jules Pascin
    Frederick Pauling
    A. Phillips
    Juliet Stuart Poyntz
    Maurice Prendergast
  - R, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Adelaide Roosevelt
  - S, 1913-1921 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Florence Saltzberg
    Boris Schatz
    M. Schwartz
    S. R. Slavsky
    John Sloan
    Maurice Sterne
    Alfred Stieglitz
    Elizabeth Stieglitz
    Joseph Suib
  - V, circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    William Vaughn (?)
  - W, 1905-1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    A. Walkowitz
    Max Weber
    Eva Weichsel
    Agnes Weinrich
    Herbert Wollf
    Willard Wright
  - Z, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Marguerite Zorach
    William Zorach
  - Illegible, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - People's Art Guild Form Letters, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Writings and Notes, 1915-circa 1919; Series 3; 4 Folders Box 1
  Found are writings by Weichsel and lists relating to the People's Art Guild. Writings by Weichsel concern a Jewish Museum, the People's Art Guild, and the state of art. Also found are exhibition lists and lists of works of art.
  - Writings by John Weichsel and grandson John Weichsel, 1965; circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lists of Artists, circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - LIsts of Works of Art and Exhibitions, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes, circa 1919 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Business and Financial Records, 1915-1917; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Found are records from the People's Art Guild including an account ledger, account balances notes, price lists, acknowledgement receipts for works of art received by the art guild for exhibitions, and general receipts. Acknowledgement receipts between the People's Art Guild and the artists participating in exhibitions include titles of works of art, prices, and dates.
  - Account Ledger and Balances, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Price Lists, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Acknowledgement Receipts, 1915-1916
  - Receipts, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1915-1929; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Found are printed materials from the People's Art Guild including exhibition announcements and catalogs, and blank membership materials. Also found are exhibition announcements and catalogs for other organizations and institutions, clippings, and art publications.
  - People's Art Guild Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1915-1918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - People's Art Guild Blank Forms, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1915-1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1915-1929 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Artwork, 1915-1916; Series 6; 1 Folders Box 2
  Found are drafts of exhibition announcements.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 7)